Finding Aid for Affirmative Action Office (University of Michigan) records 1969-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Affirmative Action Office (University of Michigan) records
1969-1993
University of Michigan. Affirmative Action Office.
University of Michigan administrative office responsible for developing and coordinating affirmative action programs for women, minorities and disabled faculty, staff, and students. Records include topical files, minutes, reports, photographs and audio and video tapes. This record group also includes records of the Commission for Minority Affairs and the Commission for Women, organizations originally independent, but since 1976 integrated within the Affirmative Action Office.
8710 BImu B29 Bimu B29 2
39 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Records were transferred from the Affirmative Action Office (Donor 5818 ) in various accessions.
The collection is open for research.
The University of Michigan Affirmative Action Program was developed in 1972 in response to federal laws passed in the 1960s to guarantee equal opportunity in employment for women and minorities. To comply with the federal regulations, the university developed recruiting practices and set goals and timetables for achieving equality for women and minorities in employment. Since 1970, the university has issued an Annual Compliance Report to the United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW). Much of the program's work during the early 1970s revolved around preparation of these reports and interpreting HEW criteria.
Nellie M. Varner was appointed first director of the Affirmative Action Program. Varner's main responsibility was to interpret the specific guidelines that were issued in October, 1972 by the Office of Civil Rights in the Department of Health, Education and Welfare (OCR-HEW guidelines). Her task was to create a university framework to meet these guidelines. As explained in the University Record of October 16, 1972, "These new guidelines spell out methods which colleges and universities must use in complying with Federal nondiscrimination orders. They include the setting of either percentage or numerical goals for hiring women and minorities...'The major job of my office,' says Dr. Varner, 'is in working out these procedures for monitoring to see if achievement of policy is made. After identifying deficiencies constructive recommendations can be made to the executive officers.'"
The director also served as a liaison between the university, federal government officials, and the university's Commissions for Minority Affairs and Women. The commissions were established by President Robben Fleming in 1971. His charge to the commissions was to examine university policies, procedures, and practices which might contribute to discrimination against minority groups and women, and to review the Affirmative Action Program of the university and make recommendations. The commissions and the program worked together to develop procedures for affirmative action and also submitted recommendations to the president for improving programs within the university.
In 1976 the Affirmative Action Program was reorganized. The name was changed to Affirmative Action Office and the Commissions for Minority Affairs and Women were integrated with the office. The move was designed to eliminate duplication of efforts and more efficiently focus activity on the eradication of discriminatory practices. The timing for the move was also right. Gwendolyn Baker had just been appointed the new director of the Affirmative Action Office and the two commission's chairmanships were about to expire. Charles Allemand replaced Gwendolyn Baker as director of the Affirmative Action Office in 1978.
During the 1970s and 1980s, the role of the office expanded beyond the protection of women and minorities. The groups protected by nondiscrimination laws and policies grew to include individuals with handicaps, people between the ages of 40 and 70, and veterans of the Vietnam War. In addition, the list of characteristics against which institutions could not discriminate included religion, national origin, height, weight, marital status, and sexual orientation.
In 1980 Virginia Nordby became director of the Affirmative Action office. The office was divided into compliance and programs teams, with Nordby overseeing both. This division reflects the two major functions of the office, that of meeting federal affirmative action guidelines, and serving the needs of groups or individuals on campus protected by nondiscrimination laws.
According to a September, 1987 Affirmative Action Office newsletter, the compliance team is responsible for all the data retrieval, analysis, and reporting necessary for writing the reports on minority student recruitment and retention, faculty and staff employment, and affirmative action compliance required by the university and the federal government. Much of this function involves monitoring the race and gender composition of the faculty, staff, and student body; setting affirmative action goals and monitoring progress made toward achieving them; and monitoring faculty and staff recruitment (In the Affirmative, vol. 5, 1987-1988)
The program team addresses the needs of members of protected groups through grievance counseling, program development, and policy recommendations. It also provides workshops to the university community. The workshops offered include Combating Sexual Harassment; Valuing Diversity: Anti-Racism Education and Training; Stares and Stair: Achieving Attitudinal and Architectural Accessibility; Managing AIDS in the Workplace; Understanding Affirmative Action and Nondiscrimination; Recruiting and Retaining a Diversified Staff; and Managing an Aging Workforce. In 1991, the office held the first campus-wide diversity and resource forum. At the forum, people learned about the many creative programs and strategies used by different university units to make a better environment in which people of all races, creeds, and cultures, live, work, and study.
The Affirmative Action Office also works with constituency groups, which are composed of volunteers united by a common cause who are willing to work together on projects to improve the university. The office provides direct staff and financial support to such groups as the Academic Women's Caucus, the African-American Organizations Coalition, the Age Concerns Council, the Association of Black Professionals and Administrators, the Commission for Women, the Women of Color Task Force, the Men of Color Task Force, the Task Force on Sexual Orientation, and the Women's Initiative Group.
In 1988 Virginia Nordby left the Affirmative Action Office. Mary Ann Swain became the interim director. In 1989, Zaida I. Giraldo became the director. In 1992, Jimmy A. Myers took over the position as Interim Director. On February 15, 1994 the Affirmative Action Office combined with the Personnel Office to become the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action. Jackie McClain was appointed as the executive director.
The records of the Affirmative Action Office date from 1969-1993 and document the activities of the office and its predecessors and provide information about affirmative action programs at the university and the status of minority, women, the disabled and other groups on campus. The records have come to the library in a number of accessions.
The Affirmative Action Office record group is organized into five subgroups: Affirmative Action Office, 1969-1993; Commission for Minority Affairs, 1971-1980; Commission for Women, 1970-1985; Council for Minority Concerns, 1979-1983; and Advisory Committee on Affirmative Action Programs, 1977-1986. The Affirmative Action Office subgroup includes records created or acquired by the Office. The other subgroups represent various university units that were merged into or whose function were taken over by the Affirmative Action Office.
Subjects:
Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Discrimination in employment--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. Affirmative Action Office.; University of Michigan. Commission for Minority Affairs.; University of Michigan. Commission for Women.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Friedan, Betty.; Handicapped persons.; International Women's Year, 1975.; Rowing.; Mud Bowl, Ann Arbor, Mich.--1970s.; Women.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Varner, Nellie M.
Genre/Form:
College publications.; Sound recordings.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Affirmative Action Office
  The Affirmative Action Office subgroup is divided into five principle series: General Files, 1969-1993; Affirmative Action Coordinators; Audio-Visual Materials; Reports; and Title IX. Materials belonging to each of these series, and the General Files in particular, may have been received in more than one of the accessions and there may be overlaps in the date spans among the accessions.
  - General Files
    The General Files are largely topical files created by the Affirmative Action Office. They are organized into subseries representing the files received in each of the major accessions. Each of the subseries covers a span of years and is arranged alphabetically. There is considerable overlap in the time spans of the various subseries.
    - 1970-1978
      The General Files for 1970-1978 include Availability Assessments, Compliance Program Reports, Goals and Timetables, and correspondence with the Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW). Availability Assessments were projections of retirements, resignations, and new positions, and the pool of women and minorities available to fill these positions. These projections were used to set goals and the timetables for achieving them. Compliance Program Reports were compiled by the Affirmative Action Office from data gathered from all of the schools and departments.
      Other significant files relate to the Hayes Study. Robert H. Hayes and Associates, an outside consulting firm, was hired to provide the university with improved systems for merit review, merit promotion and transfer, and to develop a comprehensive personnel compensation policy to cover professional and administrative employees. The Management Advisory Group made recommendations to the executive officers on professional and administrative plan implementation.
      - Affirmative Action Program Plan, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Analysis of Affirmative Action Program, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
      - Availability Assessment
        - 1970, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
        - 1976-1978 (Box 1)
      - Compliance Program Reports
        - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
        - 1970-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
        - 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - 1973-1974, 4 folders (Box 1)
        - 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Director of Affirmative Action Programs, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Executive Order No. 11246 (Equal Opportunity Act), 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - Goals and Timetables
        - 1971 (Box 2)
          (University)
        - 1972 (Box 2)
        - 1976 (Box 2)
          (Medical School)
      - HEW Correspondence and Related Materials
        - 1970-1972 (Box 2)
        - 1971-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Memoranda, 1971-1976 (Box 2)
      - Minorities, 1969 (Box 2)
      - Professional and Administrative Employees (Box 3)
        - Management Advisory Group, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
        - Robert Hayes Study, 1971-1973 (Box 3)
        - Steering Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Senate Assembly Resolution Re Affirmative Action, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Title IX (Implementation of Education Amendments of 1972 Prohibiting Sex Discrimination in Education), 1974-1975, 1972-1975
        - Varner, Nellie M., 1973 (Box 3)
    - 1969-1985
      Major topics in the 1969-1985 General Files include reports dealing with affirmative action programs and the status of minority students, the United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Publicity (generally newspaper and magazine clippings specifically discussing events at University of Michigan), UM employee information, student financial aid information, and utilization analysis.
      - Affirmative Action Program
        - 1971 (Box 8)
          - Women, 4 folders (Box 8)
        - 1973 (Box 8)
        - 1973/74
          - College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LSA) (Box 8)
          - Vice-Presidents
            - State Relations and Planning (Box 8)
            - Student Services (Box 8)
            - University Relations and Development (Box 8)
        - 1975-1978
          - Veterans (Box 9)
        - 1976-1980
          - Affirmative Action Program (Box 9)
        - Staff Composition by Racial Group, 1971-1972; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Attitude Survey, UM Staff, 1977 (Box 9)
      - Child Care, North Campus Proposal, June 1981 (Box 9)
      - Compliance Reports, February 1967; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Employee Information Reports
        - February 1968 (Box 10)
        - February 1969 (Box 10)
      - General, 1972-1985 (Box 10)
      - Health, Education and Welfare, U.S. Department of
        - Annual Report
          - 1971-1972 (Box 10)
          - 1972-1973 (Box 10)
        - Compliance Review
          - Correspondence
            - External, 1977-1978 (Box 10)
            - Internal, 1977-1978 (Box 10)
            - Internal, 1978-1979 (Box 10)
          - General, 1977-1978 (Box 10)
          - On-Site Review, December 12-16, 1977 (Box 10)
          - Operation Common Sense, 1978 (Box 10)
          - Resource Documents, 1977-1978; 3 folders (Box 11)
        - Correspondence
          - 1970-1971 (Box 11)
          - 1971-1972 (Box 11)
      - Departmental Employee Breakdown [oversize print-out], February 1, 1973 (Box 11)
      - Policy, Standard Practice Guide (Box 11)
      - Publicity
        - General
          - 1969-1981, 1984; 14 folders (Box 11)
          - Miscellaneous Dates (Box 11)
        - Women Athletics, 1971-1981 (Box 11)
      - Racial Identification, 1972-1974 (Box 12)
      - Students Receiving Financial Aid-Report re Characteristics
        - 1975-1976 (Box 12)
        - 1976-1977 (Box 12)
        - 1977-1978 (Box 12)
        - 1978-1979 (Box 12)
      - Summaries of Employment and Affirmative Action Data by EEOG Occupational Groups, 1980-1981 (Box 12)
      - Symposia re Women, 1969-1970 (Box 12)
      - Technology Council of Michigan, Minority (Box 12)
      - Title IX, A Self-Evaluation, 1976 (Box 12)
      - Utilization Analysis Report (Projections for 1976/77 to 1979/80), 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Work Force Data, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
    - 1970-1986
      The subseries, General Files, 1970-1986 includes materials relating to the Departments of Health, Education and Welfare and the Department of Labor; Graduate Employees Organization; Minorities and Minority Students; Personnel; and Women, particularly regarding the International Women's Year, 1975-1976.
      - Academic Affairs Affirmative Action Committee, 1974-1976; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Advisory Committee on Affirmative Action Program, 1977-1979; 1982-1983; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Affirmative Action Compliance Program, 1975-1983; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Affirmative Action Office
        - Operations Committee
          - General, 1978-1979; 3 folders (Box 13)
          - Systems Plan, October 1978 (Box 13)
        - Orientation Package, 1975 (Box 13)
        - Program Plans, 1975-1978 (Box 13)
        - Reorganization Committee, 1975-1978 (Box 14)
        - Staff Meetings, 1979-1980; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Affirmative Action Report, UM-Flint, 1972-1974 (Box 14)
      - Appointment Process
        - Recruitment, Workshop on Women and Minority Faculty, 1975 (Box 14)
        - Reports, 1978 (Box 14)
        - Training, Affirmative Action Task Force on, 1979 (Box 14)
      - Committee on Institutional Cooperation, 1973; 1976-1979; 5 folders (Box 14)
      - Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills, 1977-1978 (Box 14)
      - Compliance
        - Availability Assessment
          - 1976, 1978-1979; 4 folders (Box 14)
          - 1979 (Box 15)
        - Department of Health, Education and Welfare
          - 1970
            - Compliance Review (Box 15)
            - Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
          - 1971
            - Compliance Review (Box 15)
            - Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
          - 1972
            - Compliance Review (Box 15)
            - Compliance Report, 2 volumes (Box 15)
            - Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
          - 1973
            - Compliance Review (Box 15)
            - Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
            - Title IX (2 folders, includes 1972) (Box 15)
          - 1974
            - Compliance Review (Box 15)
            - Title IX Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
          - 1975
            - Compliance Review (Box 15)
            - Title IX Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
          - 1976
            - Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
            - Self-Evaluation (Box 15)
            - Self-Evaluation Report (Box 15)
            - Title IX Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
          - 1977
            - Title IX Internal Correspondence (Box 15)
          - 1978
            - Title IX Internal Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 15)
        - Department of Labor
          - Desk Audit, 1978; 2 folders (Box 16)
          - Internal Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 16)
        - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, EEOC Reports, 1975 (Box 16)
        - Skill Inventory, 1979 (Box 16)
        - Task Force on Affirmative Action, 1978-1980 (Box 16)
        - Utilization Analysis, 1978 (Box 16)
      - Graduate Employees Organization
        - Affirmative Action Plan, 1975-1976 (Box 16)
        - Contracts, 1975-1977 (Box 16)
        - General
          - 1974 (Box 16)
          - 1975-1977 (Box 16)
      - Grievances and Complaints
        - Appeal Procedures Revision, 1973-1974 (Box 16)
        - Procedures, 1972 (Box 16)
        - Procedures Revision in Standard Practice Guide, 1975 (Box 16)
        - Student Grievance Procedure Revision, 1977 (Box 16)
        - Task Force on Grievances, Complaints and Counseling, 1979 (Box 16)
      - Handicap Accessibility
        - Handrail Survey, 1971 (Box 16)
        - Curb Cuts, 1973 (Box 16)
        - Snow Removal, 1978 (Box 16)
        - Parking, 1979 (Box 16)
      - Historical Data (Box 16)
      - Internships, 1973-1975 (Box 16)
      - Internship Study, 1980 (Box 16)
      - Minority
        - Black Faculty and Staff Association, 1974-1977 (Box 16)
        - Ethnic Institute Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 16)
        - Opportunity Program, 1979-1983 (Box 17)
        - Task Force on Minority Concerns Report, 1979 (Box 17)
        - Task Force on Minority Student Concerns, 1978-1980 (Box 17)
      - Minority Student Report
        - 1977-1978 (Box 17)
        - 1978-1979 (Box 17)
        - 1979-1980 (Box 17)
      - Monitoring
        - Salary Office Position Study, 1974 (Box 17)
        - Task Force of Academic Affairs Committee on Promotions, 1978-1979 (Box 17)
      - Personnel
        - Data Reports, 1971-1981 (Box 17)
        - Employment Applications Revision, 1975-1977 (Box 17)
        - Exit Questionnaire, 1980-1981 (Box 17)
        - General, 1975-1980 (Box 17)
        - Maternity, 1977 (Box 17)
        - Minority Recruitment, 1972-1977; 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Part-time Employees, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
        - Performance Appraisal, 1974-1981 (Box 17)
        - Policies Subcommittee, 1972-1975 (Box 17)
        - Retirement Task Force, 1975-1980 (Box 17)
        - Salary Review, 1972 (Box 17)
        - Salary Study, 1976 (Box 17)
        - Staff Survey, 1977 (Box 17)
        - Student Employment Program, 1974-1978 (Box 17)
        - Training
          - General, 1978-1979 (Box 17)
          - Orientation for New Employees, 1975 (Box 17)
          - Reports, 1973-1975; 4 folders (Box 18)
          - Seminar re Handicapped, 1977; 1979; 2 folders (Box 18)
          - Supervisor Training in Plant Department, 1974 (Box 18)
          - Task Force on Training Report, 1979; 2 folders (Box 18)
        - Troubled Employee Study Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 18)
      - Policies, 1975-1979; 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Purchasing Department, 1972-1973 (Box 18)
      - Student Counseling Report, 1976 (Box 18)
      - Title IX
        - Employment, 1975-1976 (Box 18)
        - Student Grievance Procedures, 1976-1977 (Box 18)
      - Vice-President
        - Development and University Relations, 1975-1979 (Box 18)
        - Research, 1973-1975 (Box 18)
      - Women
        - Career Fair, 1977-1980; 4 folders (Box 18)
        - Central Coordinating Committee, 1977-1979 (Box 19)
        - Commission for
          - Founders, 1985 (Box 19)
          - Miscellaneous, 1977-1986; 2 folders (Box 19)
        - International Women's Year
          - Budget, 1975-1976 (Box 19)
          - Events
            - Conference, November 15, 1975 (Box 19)
            - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
            - United Nations Decade for Women, 1980 (Box 19)
          - Film Festival, 1975 (Box 19)
          - Final Report, 1975-1976 (Box 19)
          - General, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 19)
          - Honorary Degrees, 1975-1976 (Box 19)
          - Intra-University Plans and Projects, 1975-1976 (Box 19)
          - National Organization of Women, 1975-1976 (Box 19)
          - Publicity and Press Releases, 1975-1976 (Box 19)
          - Report, Informal, 1975-1976 (Box 19)
          - University Planning Committee, 1975 (Box 19)
    - 1971-1987
      Data and background material for the Department of Labor Compliance Reviews and files on handicap programs and issues together account for the bulk of the 1971-1987 General Files subseries. There is more documentation of handicap issues than in the previous accessions, and there is especially good coverage of the university's observance of the United Nations' International Year of Disabled Persons (1981). A summary of the events and activities sponsored by the university during that year can be found in the "Final Report" (box 22). Files on "Minorities" and on "Women" contain substantial information regarding "Minority Women's Career Conferences" (boxes 22-23), "Women's Career Fairs" (box 24), and the "Women's Network" (box 24). The Career Conference and Career Fair files reflect the university's continuing interest in aiding the professional development of women by providing practical information on career options through workshops, help in developing basic skills, and inspiration through well-known key-note speakers. It is clear from these files that the university's commitment focuses not only on women of minority status, but also in general on female staff and students of the university, as well as women in and around the community of Ann Arbor. The Women's Network functions as a liaison group between various women's organizations on campus, and includes representatives from the Affirmative Action Office, the Commission for Women, the Center for the Continuing Education of Women, and the Academic Women's Caucus. Network files include budget reviews, correspondence, and minutes; subjects include child care, sexual harassment, and tenure of women faculty. Unique to this subseries are general files which document the university's policies on "Sexual Harassment" and "Sexual Preference".
      - Affirmative Action Awareness Week, 1979 (Box 20)
      - Affirmative Action Compliance Program, 1980-1981 (Box 20)